How do you know you want to use a composable verses that you tell method?
Oh, I love it. You read my mind. Let's move on to this. Composable verses you tell it to ease.
So that's exactly it. So I think most people, they see this and they're like, cool, I'm just going to cram everything in composables.
Right? Because it's kind of easy. It works. I mean, let's be honest. It does work. Nothing wrong with that. However, in this discussion of, you know, in case for those who are newer to the industry,
what's actually really common in a lot of enterprise code bases, too, is this either U-tills, a way, whoops, wrong folder.
There is usually some sort of U-tills folder or utilities. And so when differentiating between the two, I would say the key thing here is that composables,
if you think about a composable, it's a term originated from the fact that it's the view composition API, meaning that it's using view things.
And so oftentimes this means it's regarding some sort of stateful UI, whether it's using reactive data with, like, rest, reactive or lifecycle methods.
On the other hand, utilities are really like, when you think of low dash, when you think of moment JS, these are things that have like generic purpose,
and really, in some ways, are kind of more that pure function mentality. Right? There, for one specific thing, whether it's like two uppercase, whatever, you choose your pick,
those are usually what I consider more of the utilities, is that they really have nothing to do with view.
And so in this regard, you might say, well, form a task that a label doesn't technically have any view things on it.
But what we could say with confidence though, is that this particular bit of, like, let's call it a search algorithm is specific to tasks.
Right? And so unless you, we could prove that like this particular status label is going to be genericized, maybe, to a bunch of other status labels.
Again, let's assume for now that this particular logic is only associated with tasks.
So one could then make the case that it really probably does belong more so in the composables.
And I'll give you a hint, part of the reason I see this too is that we mentioned that status is a string here, but one of the things that's like a hint to what's coming is that status is not necessarily just a plain value.
And so we'll talk more about that later. This has to do with composable design.
And so here we can see here there is like there in this regard, right? We have a task list that's being dropped down.
There's a lot of filtering happening. So now this, even the question of business logic, right?
Because composable doesn't necessarily equate to business logic nor doesn't necessarily equate to utilities.
And so David gave a great talk yesterday and was talking about this.
And I do think, when you're thinking about these three kind of categories, what a lot of times people do,
especially with composables is it kind of stuff everything together because it feels like the easiest thing to do.
Right? But the problem is you end up with this kind of tight coupling when it comes to testing.
Because imagine if you want to test your business logic, but it's tied to the fact that you have to navigate to a page and then click a button and then do things.
That doesn't really make sense that your business logic really should have nothing to do with what's on the web page, right?
There should be multiple ways to execute payment functions, authentication, whatever unique value proposition your business offers.
That to me is like what David mentioned is like totally your pure functions, right?
You should be able to test those in a vacuum and they should work every time regardless of what the UI is.
Right? Utilities I would say that what separates logic from utilities is that utilities aren't related to your business, like core business, right?
You could replace them with kind of any generic thing, but like logic, because that's what some people do.
They do have a separate folder for logic.
And then that is their pure functions that resolve basically targeted to their business stuff.
And the one of the struggles with testing is that you try to test everything.
But as we know, as software developers, sometimes you just don't have the resources to do so.
You might only, and especially if your test take a really long time, you want to test your core functionality.
Separating out your business logic into like a specific, essentially a specific folder, makes it easier to go, you know what?
We're going to trust that the utilities are working and that the controls are fine, but we must test the business logic every time.
Because my mentor would say, there are only two tests any company ever needs.
Can the user log in and can they pay us? Everything else is optional, right?
And so it's a bit tongue-in-cheek, but at the end of the day, we are building things that provide values to users.
And we want to make sure there's a business model behind that.
And so that's kind of the way I would see the three paradigms.
And again, adapted to whatever you and the team see fit, whatever works best for your mental model.
And again, your utilities really do tend to be those third party libraries, your low-dash, your moment.
They just very clearly scream like, I do one thing, I do it really well, and I'm going to sit here in utilities.
And then I get brought into composables where then I start affecting state changes, maybe on modifying XYZ.
That's kind of like the high level of how I like to think of these three things.
But yeah, the same ones have like, oh, yeah, we have a question.
So you're taskless, composable, yep, screams business logic to me, because it has nothing to do specific.
Do composables give you access to props and other things by default if they're used in a component or...
Nope.
So that's a funny thing.
Yeah, it is a composable then, because it sounds like it's a function you're passing around.
Yeah, it does.
The reason why this ends up becoming a composable, at least filter tasks specifically, is because, again,
this kind of like a forecasting into the future.
What we're going to find is that this taskless parameter you're passing in is not actually always going to be a plain value.
Like, this is what the assumption is right now, but you actually cannot assume that, and I explain why in a little bit.
So what you might do, for example, is you might abstract the rest of this filter like this stuff into a generic logic function.
But then this, I would still make the case that filter tasks itself needs to be a composable, because it's going to end up dealing with reactive state one way or the other.
But this is what's interesting about that three paradigm bit is that these internal bits, like, to our point of like search term, right?
This search term filter, which to correlate for what people are thinking of is here, is correlates to, oh, that I saw the server.
I think I did.
Oh, no, I didn't.
Oh, oh, I know what I did.
I know what I did.
Okay, what I did was remember filter tasks at one point had access to all the tasks.
I added a parameter that we would have to pass it in, and I did not update the filter tasks.
This to take it in.
So this needs to be passed the task stored at tasks.
No, there you go.
Okay, this search functionality, right?
Like view, as you see here, it kind of with these two instances.
Honestly, I would make the case, again, we won't do this fully, because we want to cover other things.
But this particular snippet is so generic, right?
So this might actually be an example of, in this particular case, I would say, probably just utility function for like, you know, filter matching or whatnot.
And so it's things like that where you just slowly start to just keep breaking it and chunking it as it makes sense.
So, and then to your point of like, actually, all of this stuff can most likely be genericized too, because what this stuff is doing, again, for those who want to dive deep later, is just combining the basically the selections here.
I guess this one doesn't have that many, this one doesn't have that many.
All status.
Oh, wait, I have this view on it.
Yeah.
So I can say it completed.
So it's basically combining all the different areas.
Yep.
And then.
Yeah.
So again, as we can imagine, that can probably also be then genericized as well.
So we talked a lot about the different, like a lot of the techniques we talked about earlier, we've got in generic components that provide.
So we would want like a base search filter on a C text that just takes it in, spits it out, returns back stuff, and then it just doesn't, it doesn't care what the type is.
In our particular case, it's very specific to like returning tasks right now, but you can obviously genericize it do other things too.
Yeah.
Got a question.
I see people doing use task and use tasks.
Does it make more sense to do that than only one composable?
Use task versus use task.
Are you referring to the fact that it's named use task?
Or.
That's what I would need clarification on.
Because this is where naming's tricky, too.
People.
Yeah.
I do know people who just use the plural all the time.
I think it really boils down to what your team prefers.
Obviously it does not ultimately impact the code you write at the end of the day.
So just I would say pick a convention and then choose it.
Yeah.
They follow up was plural for everything related to a list and singular for one task.
Ah.
And they do both.
Yep.
Okay.
So that there are people.
I think the most convention you'll see is they'll pluralize it when it's a list.
But I think I showed it.
Yeah.
Here.
I'm a big fan of because that one off by one letter is the thing.
I found at least when I'm typing.
So task list is just a little bit more explicit.
And that's really what arrays are.
Ultimately there are list of things.
So I personally prefer or particularly with my parameters.
I'm not sure I would I guess to be fair.
I'm not sure I would call this use task list because that's not necessarily accurate to what you're doing either.
So if I'm being really verbose, I might just call it use task feature.
Right.
That's really what it's associating with.
It really has nothing to do with whether or not it's some plural or singular.
It's just that this is the task feature that we're basically working on.
But you know developers don't like to type so we like to shorten everything.
So I get it.
Either way, you know, I say choose whatever you prefer that should not do you much harm.